Guide to the Hermann John Weigand Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hermann John Weigand papers
1906-2005
MS 1759
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.5
(42 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings, and personal papers. The correspondence includes letters with colleagues, students, and family friends concerning various topics, including views on articles published by Weigand and colleagues, different symposia, and administrative matters. The subject files include material pertaining to Weigand's research and teaching, and the writings include Weigand's notebooks and manuscripts, as well as writings of others.Material documenting Weigand's professional and family life is also present, as are audiocassettes of Weigand and his wife doing readings and dictating letters.
Weigand, Hermann J. (Hermann John), 1892-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Hermann Weigand, 1999. Gift of the Estate of Mary Koenig Weigand, 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 22 (student recommendations) is restricted until January 1, 2050 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Box 19 (student records) from Accession 2017-m-0060 is restricted until January 1, 2044 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Hermann John Weigand was born in Philadelphia in 1892. Weigand received his bachelor's degree and a doctorate in Germanic studies from the University of Michigan, where he also taught from 1913 to 1918. Weigand then went on to teach at the University of Pennsylvania before his tenure at Yale, which began in 1929. He was a leading United States scholar of Germanic literature, with expertise in medieval literature, the age of Goethe and Romanticism, modern German poetry, and Henrik Ibsen. In 1933 his acclaimed study, Thomas Mann's Novel, Der Zauberberg; A Study, was published. Weigand taught at Yale for 32 years until retirement in 1961. He continued doing research and publishing articles, even though he lost his vision in 1965. Weigand died on September 3, 1985.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings, and personal papers. The correspondence includes letters with colleagues, students, and family friends concerning various topics, including views on articles published by Weigand and colleagues, different symposia, and administrative matters. The subject files include material pertaining to Weigand's research and teaching, and the writings include Weigand's notebooks and manuscripts, as well as writings of others. Material documenting Weigand's professional and family life is also present, as are audiocassettes of Weigand and his wife doing readings and dictating letters.
Arrangement
The original accession is arranged in chronological divisions. Accession 2017-M-0060 is arranged into five groupings by topic or format.
Weigand, Hermann J. (Hermann John), 1892-1985; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The papers are arranged in five chronological divisions: 1935-1945, 1945-1954, 1955-1965, 1965-1974 and 1975-1983. Within these divisions, there are folders of general correspondence, topical files and selected correspondence with colleagues. There is also one audiocassette of Weigand dictating letters.
  - 1935-1945
    - General (A-Z), 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 7)
    - General (A-Z), 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 14)
    - General (A-Z), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 15 - 20)
    - General (A-Z), 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 21 - 27)
    - General (A-Z), 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28 - 35)
    - Buchwald, Reinhard, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Henel, Heinrich, 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Huck, Peggy, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Jaeger, Hans, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Kegel, Friedrick, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Lachmann, Vera, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Long, Percy, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Nordmeyer, George, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Parker, Dewitt, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Salinger, Herman, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Schreiber, Carl, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Twaddell, W. F., 1940 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Victor, Karl, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Wolff, Hans, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Zerner, Marianne, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - On articles, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Departments, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Departments, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Departments, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - German V, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - On "Von der Heydt", 1940-1944 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - PMLA (Programs of the Modern Language Association), 1937-1940 (Box 4, Folder 58 - 60)
    - Refugees, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Universities, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - 1945-1954
    - General (A-Z), 1945-1947 (Box 5, Folder 63 - 75)
    - General (A-Z), 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 76 - 82)
    - General (A-J), 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 83 - 87)
    - General (K-Z), 1949-1951 (Box 7, Folder 88 - 94)
    - General (A-D), 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 95 - 98)
    - General (E-Z), 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 99 - 107)
    - General (A-Z), 1953 (Box 9, Folder 108 - 117)
    - General (A-Z), 1954 (Box 10, Folder 118 - 128)
  - 1955-1965
    - General (A-Z), 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 129 - 139)
    - General (A-Z), 1956-1957 (Box 12, Folder 140 - 151)
    - General (A-Z), 1957-1958 (Box 13, Folder 152 - 162)
    - General (A-M), 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 163 - 169)
    - General (N-Z), 1958-1959 (Box 14, Folder 170 - 173)
    - General (A-Z), 1959-1960 (Box 14, Folder 174 - 182)
    - General (A-Z), 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 183 - 194)
    - General (A-Z), 1962-1963 (Box 16, Folder 195 - 200)
    - General (A-Z), 1964-1965 (Box 16, Folder 201 - 203)
    - Fellowships, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 204)
    - Graduate applications, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 205)
    - Graduate applications, 1959-1960 (Box 16, Folder 206)
    - On "Loomis", 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 207)
    - On Thomas Mann, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 208)
    - Reprints, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 209)
    - Requisitions, 1956-1958 (Box 16, Folder 210)
    - University, 1956-1958 (Box 16, Folder 211 - 212)
    - University, 1959-1960 (Box 16, Folder 213)
    - University, 1960-1961 (Box 16, Folder 214)
    - On "Wetten & Pakt", 1962 (Box 16, Folder 215)
  - 1965-1974
    - General (A-Z), 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 216 - 218)
    - General (A-Z), 1966-1967 (Box 17, Folder 219 - 221)
    - General (A-Z), 1968-1969 (Box 17, Folder 222 - 224)
    - General (A-Z), 1969-1970 (Box 17, Folder 225 - 228)
    - General (A-Z), 1971 (Box 18, Folder 229)
    - General (A-Z), 1972 (Box 18, Folder 230 - 231)
    - General (A-Z), 1973 (Box 18, Folder 232 - 233)
    - General (A-Z), 1974 (Box 18, Folder 234 - 236)
    - Birthday, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 237)
    - Cupido, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 238)
    - On "Der Bau", 1970-1972 (Box 19, Folder 239 - 240)
    - Parzival, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 241)
  - 1975-1983
    - General (A-Z), 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 242 - 247)
    - General (A-Z), 1977 (Box 19, Folder 248 - 250)
    - General (A-Z), 1978 (Box 20, Folder 251 - 253)
    - General (A-Z), 1979 (Box 20, Folder 254 - 255)
    - General (A-Z), 1981 (Box 20, Folder 256 - 257)
    - General (A-Z), 1982 (Box 20, Folder 258 - 260)
    - General (A-Z), 1983 (Box 20, Folder 261 - 262)
    - On "Doktor Faustus", 1977-1978 (Box 21, Folder 263)
    - On "Dr. Faustus Nachtrag", 1983 (Box 21, Folder 264)
    - On "Harzreise", 1975-1976 (Box 21, Folder 265)
    - On "Persischen Heliotrop", 1977 (Box 21, Folder 266)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1980 (Box 21, Folder 267 - 268)
  - Student Recommendations, 1939-1975 (Box 22, Folder 269 - 274)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Student recommendations are closed until January 1, 2050 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Audiocassette of Weigand dictating letters, 1977; 1 (Box 23)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- Additional material, 1906-2005; Accession 2017-M-0060
  Arrangement
  The accession is arranged into six groupings: correspondence, subject files, writings, personal papers, program files, and photographs and audiovisual material.
  - Correspondence
    - 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1958-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1982-11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A-F, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A-M, 1931-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      Includes photographs of family members.
    - Batchelor, Jean - poems and letters, 1931-1945 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Bechter, Margaret, 1984-11-14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Berlin, Jeffrey B., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Biographical sketches of Hermann Weigand, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Birthday, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Birthday cards, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Birthday letter from Eric J. Ziolkowski, 1982-11-16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Birthday message from A. Bartlett Giamatti, 1982-11-17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Birthday note, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes photograph of unidentified woman.
    - Brico, Antonia (duplicates), 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Card from Renhart and Carola, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Critical Probings: Essays in European Literature, from Wolfram von Eschenbach to Thomas Mann', 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Critical Probings: Essays in European Literature, from Wolfram von Eschenbach to Thomas Mann" from the editors of the Forum for Modern Language Studies, 1984-10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Curschmann, Michael, 1970-07-07 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Das Bett" draft and Zinn letter, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dotty regarding Antonia Brico, 1947-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Drafts, in order, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dvoretzky, Edward, 1985-08 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Edelmuth, F. M., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Erika's death, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Family, 1942-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes photographs of Hermann and Mary Weigand.
    - Fred - letter, 1930-04-05 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Friesen, Gerhard with German-Canadian yearbook, 1984, 1985-12-06; 1985-12-06 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Gartner, Dr. Kurt, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Glenn, Jerry, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Goldsmith - Goldschmidt, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Gretchen and Hermann - letters, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Grunwald, Stefan, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Heller, Peter, 1966-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Heller, Peter - "Collaboration of the Primary Process in Scientific Problem Solving", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Herford, Hanna and Julius, 1942-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes photographs of the Herfords.
    - Herford, Hanna - letter with clipping and memorial book, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Herman J. Weigand correspondence and inventory, 1933-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Hermeneutics and the Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative" - letters from Blanshard, Peyre, Baade, Prelinger, Willson, Ziolkowski (including book), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Holiday and birthday notes, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Johannus - letter in Latin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jonas, Klaus, 1989-1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs of Doris and Klaus Jonas.
    - Kahler, Alice, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Koenig, Mary, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Koenig, Mary and Weigand, Hermann, 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lappland, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Moe, 1954-10-06 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - MacKillen, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Mann, Thomas (photocopies), 1927-1951 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Mann, Thomas (photocopies), 1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript of German poetry from Howard Stern, 1981-05 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Marion, 1975, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Metzger, Michael, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Meyer, Herman, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miner, Felicia Jennings, 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Miner, Felicia Jennings regarding Quiddity, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - N-Z, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Nietzsche's Dionysus-Ariadne Fixation" and letters, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Nordmeyer, H. regarding Selmer's Brendanus paper, 1940-09-1940-12 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Nordmeyer, H. regarding Selmer's Brendanus paper (copies), 1940-09-1940-12 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Olga (niece) - letter with article attached, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Personal, 1944-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Quiddity, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Regarding "Magic Mountain", 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Regarding "Spiritual Therapy", 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Regarding writings (some writings enclosed), 1967-1984 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Sievert, E. A., 1954-1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Spiritual Therapy in Parzival", 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Thank-you note from Lu and Eric, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of unidentified baby.
    - Thank-you note from Ruth and Henry, 1981-01-15 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tribute to Erika Weigand from Vera Lachmann, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Uhse, Bodo from Hermann Broch, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified correspondent, letter in German, 1977-05-05 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Wapnewski, Dr. Peter, 1955-10-18 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Weigand, Else, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Weigand, Erika, 1936-1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Weigand Fellowship donors, 1987-2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Weigand, Frances, 1934-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Weigand, Hermann regarding "Hermeneutics and the Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative", 1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Weigand, Martin, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Wexler, Henry, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Wilcox, Clifford - Michigan, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Winer, Herbert, 2005-08-01 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - World War II - Parkie, Boucke, et cetera, 1939-1952 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Writings of others
      - Born, Jurgen, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Brohner, Luise, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Deschners, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Goldsmith, Ulrich, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Henel, Heinrich, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Kelletat, Alfred, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Loose, Gerhard, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Martini, Fritz, 1958-11 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Murmel, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Nelson Jr., Lowry, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Primer, Irwin, Undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Remak, Henry H. H., 1983 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Sammons, Jeffrey, Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Scharpenberg, Margot, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Spahr, Blake Lee, 1978-07-18 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Scher, Steven, 1982-11-17 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Stern, Howard, 1976-1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - Ziolkowski, Eric J., Undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Ziolkowski, Jan M., 1977-07-08 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Ziolkowski, Theodore, 1970-1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Xerox copies of letters, 1975-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ziolkowski, Theodore - "Modes of Hesse's Political Allegory: A Platonic View", 1983-06 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ziolkowski, Theodore regarding "Hermeneutics and Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative", 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ziolkowski, Yetta Joy and Saskia, 1993-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Includes photograph of friends.
  - Subject files
    The subject files contain two folders of student records that are closed until 1 January 2044 by Yale University policy. Contact Public Services for information on requesting access to restricted university records.
    - Bibliography, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Copies of title pages signed by Thomas Mann, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Critical Probings: Essays in European Literature from Wolfram von Eschenbach to Thomas Mann" flyers, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Die Deutbarkeit von Kafkas Werken" by Ingeborg C. Henel, 1969-12-05 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Die Schatzole", Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Geographia" map of London, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - German newspaper clipping, 1968-01 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Greenberg, Leonard, Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Hermann J. Weigand and a Letter from Thomas Mann: The Critical Dialogue" by Theodore Ziolkowski, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Hermann Weigand Fellowship, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "How Kipling Taught Me to Write" essay, Undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - I.D. 450 class notes and grades, 1969- (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Student records are restricted until 2044 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
    - Index cards with bibliographic information, Undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "Kafka der Dichter" by Friedrich Beissner, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Kinderkunst" by Corrado Ricci, 1906 translation, Undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "L'arte dei Bambini" by Corrado Ricci and notes, 1906? (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1961-1962, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - List of book orders and recommendations, 1970-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - List of publications since "Fahrten und Funde", 1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "Literatur und Kritik" journal, 1966-07 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "Lyrik und Prosa" journals, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Memoranda book, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Meyer, Heinrich writings, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Minwax pamphlet, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes in loose booklet, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - New Yorker magazine, 1946-08-31 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper article about summer teaching, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings and reviews on "Fahrten und Funde", 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Nordmeyer's translation of Rilke's "Duino Elegies", Undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Note on Plato in Latin, Undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Notebook with lists of readings, 1963-1970 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Notebook with list of readings and authors' names, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Notes and translations of letters between Anna Freud and Eva Rosenfeld, 1930, 1987; 1987 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Notes from January 1953 (including some publications), 1953-01 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Notes in German on Gunther Bittuer and Peter Heller, Undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Notes on French, Undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Notes on Hamlet, Undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Notes on letters, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Notes on purchasing books, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Notes on the publication of "Critical Probings: Essays on European Literature from Wolfram von Eschenbach to Thomas Mann" (photocopies), Undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Notes on travel itinerary, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      Includes photograph of Erika Weigand and Felicia Jennings Miner.
    - Pastor Weigand's poetry, Undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Review of "Critical Probings: Essays on European Literature from Wolfram von Eschenbach to Thomas Mann" by Harry Zohn, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Review of "Surveys and Soundings in European Literature" by Heinrich Meyer, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Review of "Wolfram's Parzival: Five Essays and an Introduction", 1969 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Rilke, Undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Schmidt-Weigand interview, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Scrap, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "St. Nicholas Illustrated Magazine for Boys and Girls", 1907-04 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Stenbuck writings, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Title page of "The Poetry of Conrad Ferdinand Meyer", Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "Trotzdem Humane Politik" booklet, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - V. Dietrich composition book, 1966? (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Visionen Einer Besseren Welt in Namen Goethes" manuscript with notes, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Wilcox, Clifford - "World War I and the Attack on Progress of Germany" at Michigan, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Ziolkowski - "Hermann Hesse: des Viete Lebenslant", 1967-03 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Ziolkowski, Jan - writings, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Writings
    - "A Close Up of the German Peasants' War", 1942 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Addressed to Mary, 1942-1956 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - "Auf Den Spuren von Hauptmanns Florian Geyer", 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Brand notebook, Undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Brauders' Main Currents..." notebook, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - "Bruch's Death of Vergil" program notes, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Champion notebook, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Corrado Ricci 1st draft - our translation, 2000-09-06 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence from "Modern Language Notes", 1941-04 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Das Bett", Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "Das Verhaltur's des Auton Reiser zur Werther" notebook, 1913-04-02 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Der Erurahlte" papers, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - "Der Narr in Christo" notebook, 1913-02-15 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Die tote Maus", 1984 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "The Digressions Apropos of Hobbes", 1914-03-02 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "Du Deutsche Literatur des 19. Jahrhunderts", 1911-11-27 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "Eine Bibliographie der Schriften von Hermann J. Weigand", Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "Ethics" (Hegel) notebook, 1912-05-14 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "The Ethics of Schopenhauer" notebook, 1912-05-28 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "Euphorion", 1964 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - "Festschrift - Henel - Fink - Verlag", 1969 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "Fichte's Ethics" notebook, 1912-04-16 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "Five Prefaces to Five Unwritten Books" rough draft, Undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - "The Five Stage Phenomenology: A Criticism" notebook, 1914-05-06 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - "Freidrich Schlegel" notebook, 1912-05-13 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - "Gottfried Keller" notebook, 1911-12-18, 1912-01-08; 1912-01-08 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - "Hebbel's Theory of Tragedy" notebook, 1913-05-23 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - "Heine in Paris: Friedrich Hirth's Commentary on the Letters 1831-1844", Undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - "Hellenismus und Nazarenismus in Heines Dichten und Denken" with notes enclosed, 1915-1916 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Herder notebook, 1912-07-06 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Hermann Broch's Die Schuldlosen: An Approach", 1953 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Hermeneutics and the Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative", 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Hermeneutics and the Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative" (packaged), Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Hermeneutics and the Proliferation of Legend in New Testament Narrative" (several copies, with clippings enclosed), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Kant notebook, 1912-03-12 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Keats' Ode on a Grecian Urn" notebook, 1912-12-10 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "Madame Bovary" essay, 1912-07-20 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Material related to "Nietzsche's Dionysus-Ariadne Fixation", Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)